A Guide to the Papers of John Randolph of Roanoke, 1781-1860, [n.d.]
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Letters and Documents
  - John Randolph to Thomas A. Morton, 1831 December 6, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. #10392. (Box-folder 7:53)
  - John Randolph to Robert Carrington, 1831 December 14, ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l.; #15041. (Box-folder 7:53a)
    Randolph reviews a long feud he and Carrington have had over a road through Randolph's property. Randolph also accuses Carrington of slandering a neighbor in the presence of John Marshall.
  - John Randolph to Joseph Vance, 1831 December 20, ALS, 6 pp. on 2 l.; with attached address leaf, with partial wax seal; docketed; postmarked Charlotte Court House VA, December 21? #8382. (Box-folder 7:54)
  - Prince Lieven to John Randolph, [1831], AL, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with separate address leaf, with wax seal. #3339. (Box-folder 7:55)
  - John Randolph to John R[andolph] Bryan, 1832 February 11, AL, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf, with wax seal; postmarked Charlotte Court House VA, February 13. #3400. (Box-folder 7:56)
  - John Randolph to "John Coalter or John Randolph Bryan," 1832 February 13, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf, with partial wax seal; postmarked Charlotte Court House VA, February 17; in mylar sleeve. #3400. (Box-folder 7:57)
  - John Randolph to John Rowan, 1832 August 16, ALS; photostat; with typed transcription. #5464. (Box-folder 7:58)
  - John Randolph to John R[andolph] Bryan, 1832 August 23, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Charlotte Court House VA, August [24]. #3400. (Box-folder 7:59)
  - John Randolph to "The Department of State," 1832 September 22, AL, 1 p.; with attached address leaf, with wax seal; postmarked Charlotte Court House. #3432. (Box-folder 7:60)
  - John Randolph to [William] Leigh, 1832 September 29, ALS, 1 p.; with attached partial address leaf; Barrow. #3339. (Box-folder 7:61)
  - J[ohn] B[rockenbrough] to John Randolph, 1832 October 16, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Richmond VA, October 16. #3339. (Box-folder 7:62)
  - John Randolph to [William Cullen] Bryant, 1832 November 4, ALS, 1 p. Part of letter held together with scotch tape. #8811. (Box-folder 7:63)
  - John Brockenbrough to John Randolph, 1832 November 8, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Richmond VA, November 8; Barrow. #3339. (Box-folder 7:64)
  - John Randolph to James Mercer Garnett, 1832 November 24-25, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked November 26; Barrow. #1883. (Box-folder 7:65)
  - S[amuel] P. C[arson] to John Randolph, 1833 January 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l. #5912. (Box-folder 7:66)
  - John Randolph to Peter Browne, 1833 January 21, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf, with wax seal; postmarked Charlotte Court House, January 2[1]. #9506. (Box-folder 7:67)
  - John Randolph to Samuel P. Carson, 1833 January 27, ALS, 2 pp. 1 l.; with attached address leaf, with partial wax seal; docketed; postmarked Charlotte Court House, [January] 28. #5912. (Box-folder 7:68)
  - John Randolph Clay to John Randolph, 1833 April 1, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with separate address leaf; docketed; Barrow; postmarked Washington, April 3. (Box-folder 7:69)
  - John Randolph Clay to John Randolph, 1833 April 9, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf, with wax seal; docketed; postmarked New York NY, April 10. #3339. (Box-folder 7:70)
  - Daniel Grinnan to Joseph Bryan, 1833 May 24, AMs, 9 pp. on 3 l.; with typed extract. #2118. (Box-folder 7:71)
    Dr. Francis West's reminiscences of the death of John Randolph, copied from original by Daniel Grinnan and sent to Joseph Bryan on 1887 September 28.
  - John Randolph's Last Words, 1833 May 24, AN, 1 p. #3400. (Box-folder 7:72)
    Subscribed as written by Randolph "within hours of his death," signed and dated by Condy Raguet. Lithograph of this note also in Grinnan Papers #49.
  - Robert R. Bringhurst (John Randolph's Undertaker), [ca. 1833]?, ANS, 1 p. #3440-a. (Box-folder 7:73)
    States that Randolph's body "Measured 6 ft. 2 in Long and only 13 inches across the shoulders."
  - Notes Possibly Relating to John Randolph's Deathbed Scene, [ca. 1833], AN, 2 pp. on 2 l. Written in pencil. #3400. (Box-folder 7:74)
  - John Randolph's Will, 1835., ADS. #4358. (Box-folder 7:75)
  - Article in New York American on John Randolph's Name 1837 January 10, D, 2 pp.; photocopy. (Box-folder 7:76)
  - L. W. Tazwell to Lucinda Garland, 1844 January 11, ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with separate address leaf. #5995-a. (Box-folder 7:77)
    Note on folder claims this "letter probably was to the biographer, Hugh A. Garland. Address leaf [to Lucinda] not integral."
  - William B. Randolph to Charles Lanman, 1860 June 12, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington, June 12 1860. #8428-b. (Box-folder 7:78)
    Re: John Randolph's ancestry.
  - John Randolph to Stephen Van Rensselear, [n.y.] January 5, Saturday Night, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf, with wax seal; docketed. #6435. (Box-folder 7:79)
  - Letter Cover, John Randolph to John Randolph Bryan, [n.y.] January 20, AD, 1 p.; with partial wax seal; Barrow. #49. (Box-folder 7:80)
  - Letter Cover, John Randolph to Dr. Charles L. Carter, [n.y.] [February 13], AD, 1 p.; postmarked Washington February 1[3]? #5952-a. (Box-folder 7:81)
  - John Randolph to Joseph H. Nicholson, [n.y.] October 28, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf, with wax seal; postmarked Richmond VA, October 28. #4319-b. (Box-folder 7:82)
  - J[ohn] Coalter to Mrs. Coalter, [n.y.] November 26, ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. #2118. (Box-folder 7:83)
  - John Randolph to [John] Coalter, [n.d.] Sunday Morning, ALS, 1 p.; docketed. #3400. (Box-folder 7:84)
  - J[udith] R[andolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.] Monday Morning, ALS, 1 p. #3400. (Box-folder 7:85)
  - J[udith] R[andolph] to John Randolph, [n.d.] Tuesday, ALS, 1 p.; with address on verso. #3400. (Box-folder 7:86)
  - J[udith] R[andolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.] Tuesday Night, ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. #3400. (Box-folder 7:87)
  - John Randolph to James Brown, [n.d.] Friday, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #9371-h. (Box-folder 7:88)
  - John Randolph to Henry Carrington Friday, ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. #5718-e. (Box-folder 7:88A)
    Mrs. Brockenbrough, sending his "best wishes for a pleasant journey, not only on this occasion but thro life."
  - [Albert] Gallatin to John Randolph [n.d.] Friday morning, ANS, 1 p. on 1 l. #5718-e (Box-folder 7:88B)
    Gallatin invites Randolph to dine with him tomorrow.
  - J[udith] R[andolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.] Friday night, ALS, 1 p. #3400. (Box-folder 7:89)
  - Letter Cover, John Randolph to John Randolph Bryan and Thomas Marsh Forman Bryan, [n.d.], AD, 1 p. #3400. (Box-folder 7:90)
  - J[ohn Randolph] to J[ohn] Randolph Bryan, [n.d.], ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; Barrow. #2118. (Box-folder 7:91)
  - John Randolph to [Miss Coalter], [n.d.], ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #2118. (Box-folder 7:92)
  - John Randolph's Notes on American Political Figures and others and the United States System of Government, [n.d.], AMs, 1 p. #10937. (Box-folder 7:93)
  - John Randolph's Book Lists, [n.d.], AD, 7 pp. on 2 l. #3400. (Box-folder 7:94)
  - Fragment of a Speech by John Randolph, [n.d.], AMs, 2 pp. on 1 l. #3400. (Box-folder 7:95)
  - Notes for a Speech by John Randolph in response to [Edward?] Everett address, [n.d.], AMs, 2 pp. on 1 l. #8811. (Box-folder 7:96)
  - Fragment of Charlotte Smith's "Elegiac Sonnet XXXIX," [n.d.], AMS, 1 p.; fragment in unidentified hand. #2118. (Box-folder 7:97)
  - A List of Various Randolphs Epitaphs on Turkey Island, [n.d.], AMs, 6 pp. on 3 l.; Barrow. #2118. (Box-folder 7:98)
    Tombstone inscriptions of Richard and Jane Randolph, William Randolph, and Isham Randolph.
  - Miscellaneous Genealogical Material about the Randolph Family, [n.d.], AMs, 4 pp. on 1 l.; Barrow. #2118. (Box-folder 8:1)
  - J[udith] R[andolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #3400. (Box-folder 8:2)
  - J[udith] R[andolph] to John Randolph, [n.d.], ALS, 4 pp. on 1 l.; with attached address leaf. #3400. (Box-folder 8:3)
  - [Judith Randolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.], ALS, 4 pp. on 2 l. #3400. (Box-folder 8:4)
  - [Judith Randolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.], ALS, 2 pp. on 1 l. #3400. (Box-folder 8:5)
  - [Judith Randolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.], ALS, 3 pp. on 1 l. Deteriorated and brittle, along old folds. #3400. (Box-folder 8:6)
  - [Judith Randolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.] [post 1801], AL, fragment, 4 pp. on 2 l. #3400. (Box-folder 8:7)
  - [Judith Randolph] to [John Randolph], [n.d.] [post 1802], ANS, 1 p. #3400. (Box-folder 8:8)
  - T[homas] Spring Rice to John Randolph [n.d.], ALS, 1 p. on 1 l. #5718-e (Box-folder 8:8A)
    Rice sends an invitation to attend his committee meeting on the next day at King's Arms Court.
  - Unidentified to John Randolph, [n.d.] [post 1818], ALS, 1 p.; photostat, location of original unknown. #2118. (Box-folder 8:9)
  - John G. Whittier, "Randolph of Roanoke" stanzas 13 and 14 [n.d.], AMs, 1 p. #10006. (Box-folder 8:10)
  - Unidentified "to his friend" containing A Portrait of John Randolph, esq.,[n.d.], ALS, copy, 3 pp.; in mylar wrapping. A copy of a letter "from -- to his friend" in another unidentified's hand providing "A Portrait of John Randolph." #11407. (Box-folder 8:11)
  - Letter cover John Randolph to John Brockenbrough, [n.d.], AD, 1 p. In an unknown, probably later hand. No accession number. (Box-folder 8:12)
- Series II: Prints
  - Portrait of John Randolph by Gilbert Stuart, [1804/1805], Color photograph. For reference use only; may not be reproduced. (Box-folder 8:13)
  - "John Randolph from an original portrait belonging to the late John Randolph Tucker" [n.d.], Derivative of portrait in Folder 13, above. (Box-folder 8:14)
  - "John Randolph," 1863, #9371-g. (Box-folder 8:15)
    "From the original painting by Chappel in the possession of the publishers. Johnson, Fry & Co. Publishers, New York."
  - Portrait of John Randolph of Roanoke, [n.d.], Cut from larger sheet; mounted. #11407. (Box-folder 8:16)
  - "The Honble John Randolph as he appeared in Congress Hall in all the Winter & Spring of 1824," [1824], Hand colored; mounted. #4152. (Box-folder 8:17)
  - "John Randolph in England," [n.d.], 2 copies. #3400. (Box-folder 8:18)
    Derivative of "The Honble John Randolph as he appeared..." above. Note on verso of copy 2: "Return to J.L. Bryan News Leader."
  - "John Randolph Esq." [n.d.], "Edwin sc." Sepia. #11319. (Box-folder 8:19)
  - "John Randolph Esq." [n.d.], "Edwin sc." With notes on (possibly by J.L. Bryan) on Randolph's pose and posture; on verso "Return to J.L. Bryan News Leader." #3400. (Box-folder 8:20)
  - "John Randolph" [n.d.], 2 copies. #10310. (Box-folder 8:21)
    "Engraved by T. B. Welch from a painting by J. Wood in possession of F.S. Key Esqr."
  - "John Randolph, Roanoke, Charlotte County, Virginia. Died 24th May, 1833, aged 60 years," [n.d.], #6287. (Box-folder 8:22)
    "From an old print." Derivative of engraving by T.B. Welch.
  - "John Randolph of Roanoke on his embarkation for Russia, on board ship 'Concord,'" [1832], Silhouette. #3400. (Box-folder 8:23)
    "Original by [W.H.] Brown, from life." On verso "return to J.L. Bryan News Leader".
  - "John Randolph of Roanoke," 1915 February 14., #10050. (Box-folder 8:24)
    "Original by W.H. Brown taken at Norfolk VA, 1832 just prior to Mr. Randolph's embarkation on board the 'Concord' for Russia. Copied by R.Y. Conrad, February 14, 1915."
  - Lithograph of John Randolph on Horseback, [n.d.], Negative photostat; location of original unknown. #5214. (Box-folder 8:25)
  - "John Randolph Esq.", [ante 1833], 1 p. #3373. (Box-folder 8:26)
    "I have been the steady, firm, constant, and strenuous advocate, to the best of my poor ability, of the oppressed people of Ireland--In the course of a not uneventful life, I have seen many things, I have seen a black swan,-- but I never have yet seen that rara avis in terries, an Irish Tory, or the man who had seen one."
  - "John Randolph," [n.d.], #3579. (Box-folder 8:27)
    "Engd. by W.G. Jackman. D. Appleton & Company."
  - "John Randolph of Roanoke," [1831], Mounted. Note at bottom, possibly in Randolph's hand: "John Randolph to Captn. W. 1831." #5842. (Box-folder 8:28)
  - Portrait of John Randolph, [n.d.], #3677. (Box-folder 8:29)
  - Portrait of John Randolph with biographical sketch, [n.d.], Removed from unidentified printed volume. #3677. (Box-folder 8:30)
  - "John Randolph of Roanoke", [n.d.], #3677. (Box-folder 8:31)
    "Engd. by J.A. O'Neill New York."
  - John Randolph on horseback, [n.d.], "A.D. Hollosy delt." #3677. (Box-folder 8:32)
  - "John Randolph," [1863], #3677. (Box-folder 8:33)
  - Portrait of John Randolph, [n.d.], #3677. (Box-folder 8:34)
  - "John Randolph," [n.d.], #3677. (Box-folder 8:35)
    "From a picture by Jarvis in 1811, at the New York Historical Society."
  - "Caricature of Jno. Randolph going to Panama," [n.d.], Contains a [copy/facsimile] of letter from John Randolph to John McAlister 1820 April 4. #3400. (Box-folder 8:36)